American Book Company Records
American Book Company Records
1801-1971
American Book Company.
3313 linear ft.
The American Book Company was formed in 1890 by consolidation of Van Antwerp, Bragg and Co., A.S. Barnes and Co., D. Appleton and Co., and Iveson, Blakeman and Co. The collection includes the records of the company which manufactured books and educational materials in several locations in the United States, with head offices in New York City; the book list embraced all subjects at all educational levels. The collection is primarily textbooks, including several editions as far back as 1840 of the McGuffey readers; also included are business records and illustrations.
148784
Biographical History
The American Book Company (ABC) was an educational book publisher that published textbooks at the elementary school, secondary school and collegiate levels. The company was formed in 1890 by the consolidation of four publishing houses: Van Antwerp, Bragg and Co., A.S. Barnes and Co., D. Appleton and Co., and Iveson, Blakeman and Co. It operated successfully as the American Book Company for more than seventy years with the public school system and other educational institutions as its main clients, publishing educational titles on accounting, agriculture, art, civics, foreign languages, history (both ancient and modern), life sciences, literature, mathematics, penmanship, physical sciences, and various levels of readers.
In the 1960s and 1970s the company passed first to Litton Industries and then to the International Thomson Organization, finally being acquired by D. C. Heath and Company in 1981. ABC was eventually absorbed into D. C. Heath and ceased to exist as an imprint.
The company employed many noted artists as illustrators for its public school textbooks, including Norman Rockwell and Frederick Remington. It is perhaps best known for its series of McGuffey Readers, which sold 120 million copies between 1836 and 1960.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The American Book Company Papers consists of general correspondence, calendars, business records, books, miscellanea, illustrations, and study charts, with correspondence and illustrations comprising the vast majority of the collection. Both ABC itself and its predecessor companies (Van Antwerp, Bragg and Co., A.S. Barnes and Co., D. Appleton and Co., and Iveson, Blakeman and Co.) are represented in the collection. The vast scope of the material provides a detailed picture of the education received by children in the American public school system in the late 19th and early 20th centuries, as well as the state of various fields of knowledge at the time.
General correspondence consists of correspondence with authors, publishers, illustrators and others in the course of ABC's publishing work. This portion of the inventory is presented as a spreadsheet to simplify sorting the material in various ways.
Business records contains a miscellaneous assortment of business-related records, including small desk calendars decorated with excerpts from American Book Company textbooks which were distributed to educators as a publicity feature, contracts, editorial forms, permissions, steps in the book production process, meeting minutes, and other similar material. No personnel records of any kind are included in the collection. At the end of the business records are several boxes of index card files, including an index to correspondence.
Books contains books published by the American Book Company and its acquisitions, and its founders and their acquisitions. There are multiple copies of many books, in which case at least one copy is the "marked copy" (that is, the Editor's Library copy, carrying annotations and/or pasted-in proofs showing changes made between printings and editions). One of the most famous American Book Company publications is the series of McGuffey's Readers; the collection includes several editions of these readers dating back to 1840. The series also includes wall posters, flash cards, and writing slates. This portion of the inventory is presented as a spreadsheet to allow sorting of the material in various ways.
Miscellanea contains photographs, artifacts and memorabilia, and a notebook recording the trips made by the company's private railroad car.
Illustrations contains photographs of people, industry, and architecture; galleys and proofs of original work by staff artists; prints, reproductions, and copies of famous paintings and sculpture; maps; and original drawings, watercolors, and paintings, all of which were used in the company's publications. It contains a number of works by noteworthy artists and illustrators, among whom are Norman Rockwell and Frederick Remington. This portion of the inventory is presented in the form of spreadsheets to permit sorting the material in various ways.
Authors and book titles for whom illustrations are present include the following:
Abreau (Gomez) & Flores: Leyendas Mexicanas, 1951
Alexander & Cormack: Bruce and Marcia, Woodsmen, 1939
Allen & Monpeurt: En Route
Allen & Wirth: This Government of Ours
Athey: Along Nature's Trails, 1936
Atticka: A First Course in Bookkeeping, 1935
Barnes and Others, The Realm of Reading: Doorways, 1941; Trails, 1941; Highways, 1940; Heritage, 1940; The American (two packages), regular edition 1940, Texas edition 1941; The English Scene, 1940
Batchelor & Vorath: Horizontes Latinoamericanos, 1955
Bauman & Erlenbach: College Bookkeeping (No book - not published
Bernstein: Judy's Ocean Voyage, 1932
Betz & Holzwarth: A Second German Book, 1933
Betz & Price: Learning German - A First Book, 1935; First Book, 1917
Bourbousson: Ecrivains Francais-d'Aujourd'Hui, 1953
Brauer: Chemistry and Its Wonders, 1938; Exploring the Wonders of Chemistry, 1938
Bradley & Upton: Air Navigation Workbook, 1943
Brigham & McFarlane: How the World Lives and Works, 1933
Brown & Butterfield: Bozo the Woodchuck, 1933
Buckley, White, Adams, & Silvernale: The Road to Reading series, 1938 (State Contract and Regular Editions for all titles), including Away We Go (A); Happy Times (B); In Storm and Sunshine (C); In Town and Country (D); Here and There (E); Around the Year (F); On Land and Water (G); Who Travels There? (H)
Buckley & White: Activity Spellers, 1931, Grades 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8
Buckley & White: Speller and Workbook, Grades 2-6 (in one package), 1936; Speller and Workbook, Grades 7 & 8 (in one package), 1936
Burns: Come and Sing, 1938
Cabot & Fanning: A New Approach to Spanish, First Year, 1942; A New Approach to Spanish, Second Year, 1945
Capen: Being a Citizen, 1947
Capen & Melchior: My Worth to the World, 1934, Regular and State Editions; My Worth to the World, Revised (included in above)
Carpenter: Canada and Our Northern Neighbors, 1946; Caribbean Lands, 1950; Our Little Friends of the Arabian Desert, 1934; Our Little Friends of China; Our Little Friends of Switzerland, 1941; Our Little Neighbors at Work and Play, 1939; Our Little Neighbors at Work and Play, 1939, Revised; Workbook for above, 1939; Our Neighbors Near and Far, 1933; Our Neighbors Near and Far, 1933, Revised (includes Regular, Gray (Pennsylvania), and New York State Editions); My Geography Workbook, 1934; Our South American Neighbors, 1942 (2 packages)
Cavanah & Myers: Handwriting for Expression, 1940; alphabet ruler; Teacher's First Book; Pupil's First Book; omnibus package of photos
Clifford: American Leaders, 1953; Yesterday in America, 1949
Cornell & MacDonald: Business Organization and Practice, 1936
Cronin: Economics and Society, 1939
Dodge and Others: Quelques Choses de Facile, 1935
Du Mont: Introductory French - A Reading Approach, 1941
Dvorak and Others: Typewriting Behavior, 1936
Elsbree: The American Teacher, 1939
Elson: United States - Its Past and Present, 1926 (see cards for illustration before 1931); Modern Times and the Living Past, 1921 (See cards. This must be for copyrights after 1931)
Evans & Coulter: First Lessons in Georgia History, 1913 (see cards also)
Foresman: Our Music in Story and Song, 1935; Songs and Pictures (First Edition titled Books of Songs); Child's Book, 1928 (See also cards) - First, Second, Third, Fourth, Fifth
Garner & Capen: Our Government (two packages; see also cards), 1930
Gerwig: Guideposts to Citizenship (Ambition, Loyalty, and Perseverance, all in one package), 1932
Gellette & Reinhardt: Current Social Problems, 1933
Goodfellow & Rosenberg: The Ace Supermarket, 1951
Gordon & Loftus: Come to France, 1939
Grayson & Lohman: Principles of Economics, 1956
Grismer & Arroyo: Buenos Amigos, 1943
Gruener & Lankelma: Introduction to Organic Chemistry, 1939
Halleck: English Literature (two packages), 1900 (see also cards); American Literature (two packages), 1911 (See also cards); The Romance of American Literature, 1934; The Story of English Literature, 1937; History of Our Country for Higher Grades, 1923 (see also cards)
Halleck & Frantz: Our United States, 1935; Founders of Our Nation, 1929 (see also cards); Makers of Our Nation, 1930 (see also cards)
Hart & Wilson: The Philippines, 1946
Healey & Faucher: France: Silhouettes et Croquis, 1950
Hesse (Peebles): Drei Erzählungen, 1950
Hill: Drei Zeitgenössische Erzähler, 1951
Hilton: Rural School Management, 1949
Hoffman: Bookkeeping, 1949; Workbook in Bookkeeping, 1949
Holmes & Hernandez: Practical Spanish Grammar, 1943
Huber: Cinder the Cat, 1931
Hughes: Rhythmic Games and Dances, 1942
Hunkins & Allen: Sod House Days, 1941
Hunter: Problems in Biology, 1931; Laboratory Problems in Biology, 1932; Science Teaching, 1934
Hunter & Hunter: Manual of College Biology, 1938
Hunter & Knopf: Mastery Tests in General Science, 1934 (two, perhaps)
Hunter & Whitman: Problems in General Science, 1930; workbook, 1932; manual, 1931; The March of Science, 1935; My Own Science Problems, plus workbook; Science in Our World of Progress
Knowlton et al.: The Westward March of Man series, including Our Beginnings in the Past, 1933; Our Past in Western Europe; Beginnings of Our Nation, 1933; Since We Became a Nation, 1934; When We Were Colonies, 1934; Our America - Past and Present, 1938
Leavell et al.: The Friendly Hour Readers (State Contract and Regular editions), 1935; Pre-Primer - Friends at Play; Primer - Ben and Alice; Book One - Playmates; Book Two - Indoors and Out; Book Three - Friends to Know; Book Four - Trails of Adventure; Book Five - The World's Gifts; Book Six - Winning Our Way; Reading Readiness Workbook for Preference; workbooks for Primer, Books One through Six
Leonard, Miles & Van der Kar: The Child at Home and School, 1942
Lothrop: The Wayside - Home of Authors, 1940
Lucas: Organic Chemistry, 1953 (Two packages)
McElroy & Younge: Toby Chipmunk, 1935
Macomber: Guiding Child Development in the Elementary School, 1941
Maddy & Giddings: Fun in Music, 1937
Marble: Home Safety, 1940
Mawhinney & Smith: Business and Professional Speech, 1950
Menge & Faunce: Working Together for Better Schools, 1953
Merrick and Others: My Typewriter and I, 1937
Nyberg: Fundamentals of Algebra, First Book, 1944; Fundamentals of Algebra, Second Book, 1945; Key to Fundamentals of Algebra, Second Book, 1945; Fundamentals of Solid Geometry, 1944
Pack: Kee and Bah, Navajo Children, 1940
Parker: Commercial Algebra, 1952
Partridge & Mooney: Education in Living - Time Out for Living, 1941
Pate: Local Government and Administration, 1954
Patenski & Wilson: The Charm String, 1943
Payne: Biology - Season by Season, 1942; Seasonal Experiences in Biology, 1943
Peattie: Rambles in Europe, 1934
Perry & Price: American History First Book, 1913 (see also cards); American History Second Book, 1914 (See also cards)
Pflueger & Moore: Das Unvergängliche, 1951
Place: Second Latin Course, 1930
Pollard: Virginia-Born Presidents, 1932
Porter & Hansen: Fields and Fence Rows, 1937
Ray: Laboratory Manual for Social Psychology, 1951
Reed: The Effective and Ineffective College Teacher, 1935
Reeder & Renner: Home Geography, 1944
Reich & Siegler: Selling to the Consumer, 1937
Reinhardt and Others: Social Problems, 1952
Riemer & Liebling: Expert Typewriting, 1949
Ross & Wallace: Short Stories in Context, 1953
Skinner & Skinner: Fun in Town and Country, 1940
Snyder & Wilson: Roots of Political Behavior, 1949
Spears: The High School for Today, 1950
Steadman pads (remnants of earlier publications)
Strayer & Upton: Social Utility Arithmetics (regular and state editions) Books 1 (1938) through 6; Social Utility Arithmetics, revision of 1951, Books 1-6
Strong: Writing Business Letters, 1950
Talbot & Pearson: Homemaking for Boys and Girls, 1935;Practical Problems in Homelife, 1936
Taylor: Dynamic and Abnormal Psychology, 1954
Van Tuyl: Mathematics at Work, 1935; Mathematics of Business, 1940; Key to Mathematics of Business, 1941; New Complete Business Arithmetic, 1947
Walden: Harness and Pack, 1935
Walker: Our Birds and Their Nestlings, 1904 (See also cards)
Warfel: American Novelists of Today, 1951; American College English, 1949
Wheat & Fitzpatrick: General Biology, 1932; General Biology, Rev., 1942; Everyday Problems in Health, 1923
Whitbeck and Others: The Working World, 1937; Manual and Key, 1939
Whitman: Laboratory Manual for Whitman-Peck Physics, 1947; Teaching Manual for Whitman-Peck Physics, 1947
Whitman & Peck: Physics, 1946 (two packages)
Wikdall: The Training of a Secretary, 1938
Williams: Toby, the Little Lost Dog, 1942
Williams: Secondary Schools for American Youth, 1948
Williams & Fink: Projects in Psychology, 1955
Wilson & Others: Our Ways of Living series, including Where Our Ways of Living Come From; Ways of Living in Many Lands; Living in the Age of Machines; Richer Ways of Living; workbooks for the above 4 titles
Wilson, Bowman, & King: This America, 1942
Study charts contains a small group of charts.
Some additional information is contained in the library's correspondence with ABC, prior to and during their donation of material. Please contact the repository listed above for more information on this correspondence.
Other Formats Available
Many of the textbooks have been digitized by Google books/Hathitrust.
Arrangement of the Collection
The primary arrangement of the General correspondence is loosely chronological from ca. 1880 to 1964; it is secondarily arranged in many repeating roughly alphabetical sequences. This portion of the inventory is presented as a spreadsheet to enable sorting in various ways.
Business records remain in original order.
Books are arranged in no particular order. This portion of the inventory is presented as a spreadsheet to enable sorting in various ways (see inventory below).
Illustrations are arranged in numerical order according to the "Drawing Number" stamped an the backing plate. Plates which are out of sequence, extra large, or unnumbered are placed at the end as well as illustration material organized by book title, beginning with Oversize 1060. To simplify locating all plates on a given topic, this portion of the inventory is presented as two spreadsheets (one arranged by plate number and location and the other by topic and plate number); see the inventory below.
Miscellanea is arranged alphabetically by topic or title.
Separated Material
American Book Company, our heritage and our history, a two-volume unpublished history of the company written by Managing Editor Mauck Brammer, has been removed from the collection and cataloged as part of the the Rare Books collection.
Other Related Finding Aids
Portions of the finding aid inventory are presented as spreadsheets to enable sorting the data in various ways. These are: the General correspondence (click here), the Books published (original accession and 1998 additions), and the Illustrations (click here and here). A more detailed explanation of each series, with a link to it, is provided at the appropriate location in the inventory below.
Subject and Genre Headings
Business and Industry; Publishing, printing and book arts; American Book Company -- Archives.; McGuffey readers.; Arithmetic -- Study and teaching.; Education, Elementary -- Textbooks -- Specimens.; Education, Primary -- Textbooks -- Specimens.; Education, Secondary -- Textbooks -- Specimens.; Educational publishing -- United States.; Geography -- Textbooks -- Specimens.; History -- Textbooks -- Specimens.; Mathematics -- Textbooks -- Specimens.; Music -- Textbooks -- Specimens.; Penmanship.; Primers -- 1800-1870.; Primers -- 1870-1950.; Publishers and publishing -- United States.; Readers (Elementary); Readers (Secondary); Science -- Textbooks -- Specimens.; Textbooks -- Publishing.; Textbooks -- United States.; Vocational education -- Textbooks -- Specimens.; Annual reports.; Artwork.; Books.; Calendars (documents); Correspondence.; Drawings (visual works); Galley proofs.; Illustrations.; Maps (documents); Paintings (visual works); Photographs.; Primers (books); Textbooks.; Watercolors (paintings); Publishers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Majority, gift of the American Book Company.
Some items (noted in inventory below) gift of Selma Ordewer, 2014.
Inventory
- General correspondence
  - General correspondence, 1801-1964 (Box 1-244)
    The general correspondence contains ABC's correspondence with its authors, illustrators, and editors, as well as with other publishers; in many, though not all, cases, an author's name is accompanied by the title of the book(s) under discussion. There are also organizations, educational institutions, and other correspondents as well as material relating to declined manuscripts, copyright, contracts, and a few meeting minutes. The material is arranged in a roughly chronological order in repeating alphabetic sequences; as a result material relating to a given correspondent or book title may be found in several different locations. To simplify locating all relevant information, this section of the inventory is presented in the form of a spreadsheet, which can be sorted by box number, correspondent, book title/subject, or date. Click here to open the spreadsheet.
    There is also a partial index to the correspondence; see Business records: Index card files: Correspondence.
- Business records
  Business records do not contain any employee files or other employee records.
  - Calendars, 1887-1963; 3 folders (Box 245)
  - Dropped books list (Box 245)
  - Design and proposition procedure (Box 245)
  - Lorna Dietz (Box 245)
  - Managers, 1919 (Box 245)
  - W.H. Dennis, obituary (Box 245)
  - Magnetism (Box 245)
  - Wilson, Ben J. (Box 245)
  - Americanism (Box 245)
  - Butler, Sheldon & Co. (Box 245)
  - Everett T. Calvert (Box 245)
  - P.L. Carret (Box 245)
  - Litton Industries (Box 245)
  - Contract form (Box 245)
  - Gillman, 1914-1931 (Box 245)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 245)
  - Editorial notices, 2 folders (Box 245)
  - Suggestions for authors (Box 245)
  - E.S. Bird (Box 245)
  - A.S. Barnes & Co. (Box 245)
  - James Baldwin (Box 245)
  - Appleton & Co. (Box 245)
  - American Book vs American Book Company (Box 245)
  - ABC - Ambrose, 1896-1914 (Box 245)
  - Aladdin Books (Box 245)
  - Blake, 1939 (Box 245)
  - Blakeman and Iveson, 1895-1896 (Box 245)
  - Brown, 1956 (Box 246)
  - Herbert G. Molden (Box 246)
  - McGuffey, William Holmes (Box 246)
  - Permission procedure (Box 246)
  - Major steps in book production (Box 246)
  - Proof corrections (Box 246)
  - Publishers Book of Trade (Box 246)
  - Merriam-Webster (Box 246)
  - Marriner, 1946-1956 (Box 246)
  - Managers' meetings, 1920-1922 (Box 246)
  - Sales offices (Box 246)
  - Samuels (Box 246)
  - School Book Publishers Society, 1907 (Box 246)
  - Filing system and policy (Box 246)
  - Forms, blank (Box 246)
  - Founders (Box 246)
  - Author biographies (Box 246)
  - Leo Gans (Box 246)
  - Harper (Box 246)
  - Russell Hinuran (Box 246)
  - War Production Board, 1942 (Box 246)
  - The Union Label (Box 246)
  - Vail (Box 246)
  - Van Antwerp, Brace and Co. (Box 246)
  - ABC Histories, Howe, 1931-1939 (Box 246)
  - Ivison, Blakeman and Co. (Box 246)
  - Edward W. Smith (Box 246)
  - State publication (Box 246)
  - State blueprints, Texas (Box 246)
  - Gilmon H. Tucker (Box 246)
  - Intercompany business, 1904-1930; 23 folders (Box 246)
  - Editorial department (Box 246)
  - Plate account and plate expense, 8 folders (Box 246)
  - Annual reports, corporate, 1964-1965; includes original printing plate for ABC logo; 2 folders (Box 247)
    Gift of Selma Ordewer, 2014.
  - Annual reports, editorial dept., 1931-1951; 4 folders (Box 247)
  - Buckingham study of typography in relation to readability in first grade materials, 1932-1933 (Box 247)
  - Policy statements for authors, copyright, copyright procedure, contract and quotation privileges (Box 247)
  - Books published 1904-1932, total number of books published each year (Box 247)
  - Statistical reports, editorial dept., 1952-1961; 3 folders (Box 247)
  - Editorial activities, education - college - international, 1962-1966; 3 folders (Box 247)
  - Editorial expenses, covers mid-1950s to mid-1960s; includes booklet of ABC type specimens from 1892 (Box 247)
  - Company biography by Mauck Brammer
    Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging.
  - Pamphlets, 2 folders (Box 247)
    One Hundred Fifty Years of Arithmetic Textbooks, (1945), by Henry Lester Smith, Merrill T. Eaton, and Kathleen Dugdale
    Alphabetical Price List (circa 1900?), American Book Company; includes instructions, "If ordering by telegraph"
    Our Textbooks, Yesterday and Today (1953), by W.W. Livengood
    Winthrop B. Smith: Creator of the Eclectic Educational Series (1971), by Mauck Brammer (in Ohio History Vol. 80 No. 1)
  - Miscellaneous publications (Box 248)
  - Prices and catalogues, 1890-1967 (Box 249)
  - Books of entry, 4 volumes (Box 250)
  - Books of Entry, 1905-1945; 2 volumes (Oversize 1)
  - Weekly reports, editorial department
    - Weekly reports, Oct. 6, 1923-Sep. 25, 1931; 4 volumes (Oversize 2)
    - Weekly reports, Oct. 3, 1931- Nov. 27, 1937; 3 volumes (Oversize 3)
    - Weekly reports, Dec. 11, 1937-Aug. 25, 1947; 3 volumes (Oversize 4)
    - Weekly reports, Sep. 1, 1947-May 28, 1951; 2 volumes (Oversize 5)
  - Index card files
    - Correspondence index, A-Z by author, several hundred cards, including Brammer's original note accompanying the donation; unclear what dates are covered, but no later than 1966 (Box 251)
    - Permissions, about 30 index cards listing permissions information for various titles (Box 251)
    - Transfers, A-D (Box 553)
    - Transfers, Ea-Z (Box 554)
    - Transfers, 1910-1927 (Box 555)
    - Declined manuscripts, circa 1930-1950 (Box 555)
    - Declined proposals (Box 556)
    - Declines and transfers, to 1910 (Box 557)
- Books
  These boxes contain publications of the American Book Company and its acquisitions, its founders and their acquisitions. There are multiple copies of many books, in which case at least one copy is the "marked copy" -- the Editor's Library copy, carrying pasted-in proofs showing changes made between printings and editions. The series also includes wall posters, flash cards, and writing slates. Items include textbooks, teachers' guides, answer keys, tests, additional instructional material, etc.
  The material is roughly arranged in repeating alphabetic sequences; as a result items relating to a given author or book title may be found in several different locations. To simplify locating all relevant information, this section of the inventory is presented in the form of two, spreadsheets, one for the original accession and another for the later 1998 accession, which can be sorted by box number, author, book title, or date.
  See also Business records: Index card files above for additional material relating to books.